Guide to the Max Ewing Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Max Ewing collection
1887-2003
1910-1934
YCAL MSS 656
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
11.45
(36 boxes)
The Max Ewing Papers consist of correspondence, writings, sheet music, photographic prints and negatives, photograph albums, scrapbooks, diaries, sound recordings, writings of others, notebooks, printed material, personal papers, and a sculpture. Correspondence includes letters from Ewing to his parents, general correspondence with friends and family, and third party correspondence regarding Ewing. Writings contain autograph manuscript and typescript drafts and printed versions of short stories, poems, essays, and other writings, including typescript drafts, corrected, of Ewing's novel, Going Somewhere. Sheet music contains printed and manuscript music by Ewing. Photographs in the collection are from Ewing's "Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits," "Carnival of Venice," Les amants de Venice" and subjects include Ewing's family and friends. The scrapbooks were made and kept by Ewing and contain reproductions of photographs of notable artists and celebrities; articles by or on Ewing, concerning his professional life as a music editor, musician, photographer, and writer; and reviews of Going Somewhere. Sound recordings are two aluminum instantaneous phonodiscs, "Speak-O-Phone personal phonographs," made by Max Ewing with Berenice Abbott and Doris Ewing. Other papers include Ewing's parents' marriage certificate, diaries, notebooks, legal documents, lists of books read by Ewing, printed material, writings on Ewing by others, and an unidentified head sculpted in clay.
Ewing, Max
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Doris Ewing (Max Ewing's cousin), Lawrence H. and Roberta Conrad, Alice de la Mar, Mark Lutz, and Carl Van Vechten, 1943. Gift of Doris Ewing and Mildred Henry, 1944. Gift of William John McAfee III, 1950. Gift of Wallace K. Ewing, 1998 and 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 34 (nitrate photographic negatives): Restricted fragile material. Some corresponding prints are available in Box 20. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 35 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 36 (clay bust): Restricted fragile material. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Printed material received with the collection was removed for separate cataloging and can be accessed by searching Orbis (Yale's Online Catalog).
Carl Van Vechten Papers (Za Van Vechten). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Max Ewing (1903-1934)
Max Ewing, American photographer, novelist, composer, pianist, and sculptor. Ewing was born in Pioneer, Ohio on April 7, 1903 to John Caleb and Clara Barto Ewing, to whom he remained close throughout his life. He started playing piano at an early age. He attended the University of Michigan, where he also served as the music critic for the Ann Arbor Time-News before becoming music editor of the Sunday Magazine, a controversial publication associated with the University of Michigan Daily. Ewing moved to New York City in 1924, where he studied piano under Alexander Siloti for three years before moving to Paris to study with Marcelle Meyer. He enjoyed a successful career as a professional pianist until 1927, when he turned his attention to composition of light musical theater, writing fiction, creating sculptures, and especially photography. He published his only novel, Going Somewhere (Alfred Knopf) in 1933. It received positive reviews but did not gain him a reputation as a successful novelist.
Ewing is best known for his photography, especially the photograph collection "Carnival in Venice" and his 1928 exhibition "Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits." "Carnival of Venice" is a series of photographs of friends posed individually and together against a backdrop depicting a scene from Venice, Italy. Individuals include Muriel Draper, e.e. cummings, Paul Robeson, Berenice Abbott, George Platt Lynes, Lloyd Wescott, Dorothy Crawford, Paul Meeres, Max Ewing, Lincoln Kirstein, and Dorothy Sheldon. The collection received praise from his friends and was shown at the Waldorf-Astoria. For his "Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits," Ewing converted the walk-in closet of his Manhattan studio apartment into a semi-public portrait gallery. He covered the walls with original photographs and reproductions of images of friends and celebrities, representing New York's interracial, gay and lesbian, and artistic circles. This exhibition gained him attention and was re-installed in other New York galleries.
Ewing's nearest friends included Carl Van Vechten, who introduced him to many of the people that appear in Ewing's photographs, Muriel Draper, and the boxer Jack Pollock. He suffered from depression throughout his life and required attention from those that were closest to him. He maintained a consistent correspondence with his parents from a young age until their deaths, writing to them weekly. His father died in 1932 and his mother in 1934. Ewing spent the last few months of his life in Pioneer, Ohio before he committed suicide on June 18, 1934, by drowning himself in the Susquehanna River in Binghamton, New York.
Scope and Contents
The Max Ewing Papers consist of correspondence, writings, sheet music, photographic prints and negatives, photograph albums, scrapbooks, diaries, sound recordings, writings of others, notebooks, printed material, personal papers, and a sculpture. Correspondence includes letters from Ewing to his parents, general correspondence with friends and family, and third party correspondence regarding Ewing. Writings contain autograph manuscript and typescript drafts and printed versions of short stories, poems, essays, and other writings, including typescript drafts, corrected, of Ewing's novel, Going Somewhere. Sheet music contains printed and manuscript music by Ewing. Photographs in the collection are from Ewing's "Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits," "Carnival of Venice," Les amants de Venice," and subjects include Ewing's family and friends. The scrapbooks were made and kept by Ewing and contain reproductions of photographs of notable artists and celebrities; articles by or on Ewing, concerning his professional life as a music editor, musician, photographer, and writer; and reviews of Going Somewhere. Sound recordings are two aluminum instantaneous phonodiscs, "Speak-O-Phone personal phonographs," made by Max Ewing with Berenice Abbott and Doris Ewing. Other papers include Ewing's parents' marriage certificate, diaries, notebooks, legal documents, lists of books read by Ewing, printed material, writings on Ewing by others, and an unidentified head sculpted in clay.
All material was a gift of Doris Ewing, 1943, unless otherwise noted.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1887-1946. II. Writings, 1927-1933. III. Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits, 1928. IV. Photographs, 1887-1924. V. Scrapbooks, 1922-1923. VI. Other Papers, 1901-2003.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Composers -- United States; Gay men -- United States -- Portraits; Gays -- United States; Novelists, American -- 20th Century; Photographers -- United States; Pianists -- United States; Portrait photography -- United States; Sculptors -- United States; Songs with piano; Audiovisual materials; Diaries; Exhibition catalogs; Negatives; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Scrapbooks; Sculpture (visual work); Sound recordings; Sheet music covers; Theater programs; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Composers -- United States -- 20th Century; Novelists -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographers -- United States -- 20th Century; Pianists -- United States -- 20th Century; Sculptors -- United States -- 20th Century; LGBTQ resource; Studio portraits; Abbott, Berenice, 1898-1991; Conrad, Lawrence H. (Lawrence Henry), 1898-; Draper, Muriel, 1886-1952; Ewing, Clara Barto; Ewing, Doris; Ewing, John Caleb; Ewing, Max; Ewing, Wallace K.; Pollock, Jack; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
- Correspondence, 1887-1946; Series I; 3.78; (9 boxes)
  Arrangement
  This series is organized into three subseries: Letters from Ewing to his parents, General correspondence, and Third party correspondence.
  Letters from Ewing to his parents contains letters dating February 22, 1910 to December 25, 1933 and includes undated letters filed at the end of the subseries. Written at least weekly, these letters document Ewing's daily life, his friends and acquaintances, and his professional and personal pursuits.
  General correspondence contains letters between Ewing and family and friends. Notable correspondents include Muriel Draper, Carl Van Vechten, and George Platt Lynes.
  Third party correspondence contains letters between family and friends regarding Max Ewing. Included among the subseries are letters regarding Ewing's death.
  - Letters from Ewing to his parents
    Scope and Contents
    Letters are from Ewing to his parents, John Caleb Ewing and Clara O. Barto.
    Arranged chronologically and according to a number system (1-843) established by researcher Mark Lutz. Indices of names and dates were prepared by Lutz and are filed in Box 1.
    - 1-150, 1910 February 22-1923 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - 151-300, 1923 November 26-1927 (Box 2, Folder 8-13)
    - 301-460, 1928 January 11-1930 October 27 (Box 3, Folder 14-20)
    - 461-650, 1928 January 11-1930 October 27 (Box 4, Folder 21-27)
    - 651-843, 1930 October 30-1933 December 25 (Box 5, Folder 28-35)
  - General correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Correspondence sorted generally by last name and unsorted correspondence is filed at the end of the subseries.
    - Ailes, Edgar H. (outgoing), 1922-1934 (Box 6, Folder 36-37)
    - Bishop, Frank (incoming), 1921-1934 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Conrad, Lawrence H. and Roberta (outgoing), 1923-1934 (Box 6, Folder 39-40)
      Custodial History
      Gift of Lawrence H. and Roberta Conrad, 1944
    - de la Mar, Alice (outgoing), 1932-1934 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Gift of Alice de la Mar, 1944
    - Draper, Muriel, 1926-1934 (Box 6, Folder 42-45)
    - Ewing, A.E. (outgoing), 1925-1932 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Ewing, Clara and J.C. and Josephine Barto (incoming), 1913-1933 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Ewing, Doris, A.E., and Lotta Ewing (incoming), 1925-1934 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Ewing, Doris and other family members (outgoing), 1918-1934 (Box 7, Folder 49-50)
    - Gorden, Taylor (incoming), 1926-1932 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Henry, Mildred (outgoing), 1924-1934 (Box 7, Folder 52)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Mildred Henry, 1944
    - Larsson, Ellery (incoming), 1923-1932 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Lynes, George Platt (outgoing), 1933-1934 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Osborn, Paul (incoming), 1928-1934 (Box 8, Folder 55)
      Includes letters to J. E. Ewing
    - Ross, Cary (incoming), 1923, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - Sheldon, Dorothy Butler (incoming), 1933 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - Stettheimer, Florence (outgoing), 1934 (Box 8, Folder 58)
      Includes 1944 letter to James Babb
    - Vechten, Carl Van (incoming), 1922-1934 (Box 8, Folder 59-60)
    - Waterman, Edward (outgoing), 1932-1934 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - Various correspondents, A-R, 1924-1933 (Box 8, Folder 62-64)
    - Various correspondents, S-Z, 1923-1934 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - Letter regarding "On Looking at a Stained Glass Window" from Whimsies, 1921 May 9 (Box 9, Folder 66)
      Gift of Carl Van Vechten, 1943
    - Unsorted incoming correspondence, 1887-1934 (Box 9, Folder 67-68)
      Includes three letters to his mother from various individuals
  - Third party correspondence
    - Doris Ewing letters regarding Max Ewing, 1934-1946 (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - General third party correspondence regarding Max Ewing, 1919-1943 (Box 9, Folder 70)
      Many of these letters concern his death. Correspondents include Alice de la Mar, Carl Van Vechten, Muriel Draper, and Ewing family members
      Letters from Alice de la Mar are a gift from her, 1944
    - Lawrence H. Conrad to Carl Van Vechten, regarding Ewing's "Indipohdi", 1942 July 24 (Box 9, Folder 71)
- Writings and Sheet Music, 1927-1933, undated; Series II; 1.26; (3 boxes)
  This series contains autograph manuscript and typescript drafts of writings and sheet music by Ewing, including the typescript draft, corrected, for Ewing's novel Going Somewhere. Notes and unsorted and unidentified writings are filed at the end of the series.
  See Other Papers for writings of others.
  - "The Americans Come," typescript drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 72)
  - "Caprioles in an Opera House," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 73)
  - "The Career of Passionate Nalda: A Novel by Imlac," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - "Carl Van Vechten - His Life and Works," typescript draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - "Christening Service," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - "Concerning the Eccentricity of Thamar Tooting," typescript drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 77)
  - ["Crickett-Wickett-Pick it..."], autograph manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 78)
  - "The Curfew Bell," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - "Double Dealer," typescript draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - "The Falling Star," typescript draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - "Fifteen Impressions Or Reactions," autograph and typescript draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - "Filled with Photographs," typescript draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 83)
  - "A Film Phenomenon: Gary Cooper as an Idol of the 'Smart Set'", undated (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - "Food of Love," typescript draft and autograph sheet music, undated (Box 10, Folder 85)
  - "For the Benefit," typescript draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - "Gertrude Stein on Donald Angus," typescript draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Going Somewhere, typescript draft, corrected, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 88-92)
    Includes correspondence with Alfred A. Knopf and a contract with Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.
  - Going Somewhere, typescript draft, corrected, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 93-94)
  - "The Golden Girls: A Comedy," typescript draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 95-96)
  - "Grand Street Follies. Silver Apron Strings," printed sheet music, 1927 (Box 11, Folder 97)
    Gift of Wallace K. Ewing, 1998
  - "The Greatest Good: Screen Story Synopsis,"typescript draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - "Imlac in America," typescript draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 99)
  - "Indipohdi," typescript drafts (by Max Ewing and others), undated (Box 11, Folder 100-101)
  - The Inlander, Volume 10, no. 4, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 102)
  - "Intelligence Test," typescript draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 103)
  - "Just a Little Love Song," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 11, Folder 104)
  - "A Life Behind," typescript draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 105)
  - "Much Ado About Baby," typescript draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 106)
  - "No One In Town," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 12, Folder 107)
  - "On and Off the Isle of Youe: A Strange Story," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 12, Folder 108)
  - "On Looking at a Stained Glass Window in the U. of M. Reading Room," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 12, Folder 109)
  - "One Cannot See the Technique for the Tears," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 12, Folder 110)
  - "One Through Two Springs," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 111)
  - "Out of My Mind," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 112)
  - "Out of My Mind, Book II: New York and Other Leopards," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 113)
  - "Picayunes: Nineteen Studies in Subtlety by Imlac," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 114)
  - "The Poetry and Prose of Glenway Wescott,"typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 115)
  - "Return Ticket: A Comedy," typescript draft, 1933 (Box 12, Folder 116)
  - "Salome in Spats," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 117)
    Includes typescript drafts: "Queen in Nictitation;" "Topaz in a Trance;" "Unicorn in Grammercy Park;" "Wandering in a Phantasy"
  - "Songs," autograph sheet music, undated (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - "Sonnets from the Paranomasian," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - "Sound Stuff and Nonsense in Schopenhauer's Aesthetics of Music," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - "Ten Cents a Block," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - "Trying to Get Along," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - "Trying to Get Along," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - "The Very Nervous...," typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 128)
    Perhaps written by Jean Tucker
  - "What Am I Worth?" typescript draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Notes and first lines of poems, autograph manuscripts, undated (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Unsorted writings, undated (Box 12, Folder 126)
    Includes a typescript guest list for unidentified event
  - Binder with notes and unidentified writings, undated (Box 12, Folder 127)
- Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits, 1928; Series III; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  This series contains photographs (original and reproductions) and catalogs for Ewing's "Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits," also known as "Gallery of Incredible Portraits."
  - Photographs from envelope labeled "Pictures from the Max Ewing Closet Gallery of 'Extraordinary Portraits' v. 1", 1928 (Box 13, Folder 129-133)
  - Photographs from envelope labeled "Pictures from the Max Ewing Closet Gallery of 'Extraordinary Portraits' v. 2", 1928 (Box 13, Folder 134-135)
  - Photographs from envelope labeled "Gallery overflow (not identified) v. 3", 1928 (Box 13, Folder 136-137)
  - Typescript of catalog for "Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits", 1928 (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - "Gallery pictures (cataloged): Max Ewing Collection of 'Extraordinary Portraits' which covered the walls of his clothes closet. The numbers refer to two catalogs. A few from which the numbers have disappeared I have identified. C.V.V. 1943", 1928 (Box 14)
    Contained in an expanding file folder
  - Catalogs for "Gallery of Extraordinary Portraits", 1928 (Box 14, Folder 139)
- Photographs, 1887-1924, undated; Series IV; 2.59; (12 boxes)
  Box 34 (nitrate photographic negatives): Restricted fragile material. Some corresponding prints are available in Box 20.
  Arranged into two subseries: Photographs and Photograph albums
  This series contains negatives, photographs, and photograph albums by Ewing, including his series "Carnival of Venice" and volumes one through four of "Les amants de Venice." Many photographs have notes identifying individuals and dates. One photograph album includes mounted clippings on Ewing, including clipping on Ewing's death, added by Doris Ewing after his death.
  - Photographs
    - Nitrate negatives for "Carnival of Venice", undated
      Original expanding folder that contained the negatives is housed in Box 15
    - Mounted photographs of Ewing family, 1887-1928 (Box 15, Folder 140)
      Includes 1887 letter of recommendation for Clara Barto from J. F. Smith of the Williams County School Examiners
    - Photographs of family and friends, 1905-1932, undated (Box 15, Folder 141-149)
    - "Friends and Associates" (mounted), undated (Box 16, Folder 150-166)
    - "Friends and Associates" (mounted), undated (Box 17, Folder 167-184)
    - "Friends and Associates" (mounted), undated (Box 18, Folder 185-201)
    - "Friends and Associates" (mounted), undated (Box 19, Folder 202-215)
  - Photograph albums
    - "Carnival of Venice", undated (Box 20)
    - "Les amants de Venice" volumes 1-4, undated (Box 21)
    - "Snapshots 1932" (Box 22)
      Includes mounted clippings and printed illustrations and clippings of various individuals
    - Of friends (green), 1920s (Box 23)
    - Of friends (red), 1925-1931 (Box 24)
    - Of family and friends, circa 1931 (Box 25)
    - Of family and friends, 1920-1934 (Box 26)
      Includes mounted clippings on Ewing, including clipping on Ewing's death, added by Doris Ewing after his death
- Scrapbooks, 1922-1923, undated; Series V; 0.93; (3 boxes)
  This series contains scrapbooks made and kept by Ewing. The bulk of the scrapbooks contain reproductions of photographs of notable artists and celebrities. One scrabook compiled by Ewing contains articles by or on Ewing, concerning his professional life as a music editor, musician, photographer, and writer. Another contains reviews of his novel, Going Somewhere.
  - Eleven scrapbooks containing photograph reproductions of famous individuals, undated (Box 27, Folder 216-221)
  - Empty folder number
  - Clippings of articles by or on Ewing (large black), 1922-1928 (Box 28)
  - Clippings of reviews of Going Somewhere, 1933 (Box 29, Folder 223)
- Other Papers, 1901-2003, undated; Series VI; 1.05; (3 boxes) + 1 portfolio
  Box 35 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Box 36 (clay bust): Restricted fragile material. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Other Papers includes personal and legal papers, diaries, notebooks, an address book, "Speak-O-Phone personal phonograph" sound recordings, lists of books read by Ewing, printed material, writings of others, and a sculpture of an unidentified head. Filed at the end of the series are two writings on Ewing, "Going Nowhere: A Study of Max Anderson Ewing" by William John McAfee III and "From Pioneer to Fame and Back: The Selected Correspondence of Max Ewing" by Wallace K. Ewing.
  - Marriage certificate of Ewing's parents, John Caleb Ewing and Clara O. Barto, 1901 May 27 (Box 30, Folder 224)
  - Five diaries, 1916-1918, 1933-1934 (Box 30, Folder 225-227)
  - Two notebooks, undated (Box 30, Folder 228)
  - Address book, undated (Box 30, Folder 229)
  - "Speak-O-Phone personal phonograph" sound recordings
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "Êtes-Vous Polygame?" an interview and "Isn't It Awful?" a lament by Princess Eugène Murat (Berenice Abbott) and Max Ewing (dialogues), one aluminum instantaneous phonodisc, 1929 July 27
    - "Reminiscences and Hysterics," "An Intelligence Test," Doris Ewing and Max Ewing, one aluminum instantaneous phonodisc, 1929 August 3
  - Legal documents, 1933-1935 (Box 31, Folder 230-232)
  - List of books read by Ewing, 1920 October-1925, undated (Box 31, Folder 233)
  - "Books Read Beginning 1920," typescript draft, undated (Box 31, Folder 234)
  - "Max Ewing's Books," typescript draft, undated (Box 31, Folder 235)
  - Pamphlets relating to Ewing and friends (Box 31, Folder 236-237)
  - Pamphlets by and about Ewing (Box 31, Folder 238)
  - Clippings by and about Ewing (Box 31, Folder 239)
  - Printed material, undated (Box 31, Folder 240)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1922-1934 (Box 31, Folder 241)
  - Programs, 1925-1927 (Box 31, Folder 242)
  - "Waldorf-Astoria Daily Bulletin," printed version, 1933 February 15-16 (Box 31, Folder 243)
  - Clippings on George Antheil collected by Ewing, 1927, undated (Box 32, Folder 244)
  - Clippings and printed material relating to Ewing, 1923-1931, undated (Box 32, Folder 245-248)
  - "Going Nowhere: A Study of Max Anderson Ewing" by William John McAfee, III, typescript draft, 1950 April 1 (Box 32, Folder 249)
    Gift of William John McAfee III, 1960
    Prepared for a course taught by Norman Holmes Pearson, 1950. Includes letter to McAfee from Van Vechten, 1950 January 16, a letter from Yale University granting permission for the use of materials from the Max Ewing Collection.